Jose Cambronero

170 West 74th, Apt 712. NY, NY 10023

(As of 11/02/2015) I am a final year student in the Masters in Computer Science program at NYU, with interests in programming language theory, compiler construction, and natural language processing. I'm particularly interested in leveraging the first two areas to create well-founded systems that improve the ability to do work in analytics in general. I have work experience both in the academic and industry settings.

Education

Academic Qualifications.

New York University: Courant Institute of Mathematical Sciences

NY, NY

Masters in Computer Science

Expected May 2016

GPA: 3.8, MS Research/Thesis Fellowship Award Fall 2015, funding continued work on A2Q (an order-aware optimizing query compiler for Aquery)

University of Pennsylvania

Philadelphia, PA

Bachelor of Arts in Economics and Minor in German Studies GPA: 3.93, Phi Beta Kappa, Summa Cum Laude, Dean's List (08, 09, 10) 2007-2011

Academic Work Experience

Grader *Graduate Course in Compiler Construction*

New York University

Spring 2015, Current (Fall 2015)

I review all students' assignments and capstone compiler projects. In doing so, I provide explanations for any misunderstood concepts or areas of improvement. This involves analyzing their source code, test results, and any additional materials. Additionally, I host weekly office hours to answer any questions relating to the lectures or assignments.

Teaching Assistant

New York University

Graduate Course in Programming Languages

Fall 2014

I led weekly recitation for students in the Masters in Computer Science and Masters in Information Systems. This involved creating weekly presentations that reviewed key concepts, and providing real-world examples and exercises. I also held weekly office hours to aid students with any questions, in addition to communication via email.

Industry Work Experience

Full time.....

Non-Agency Mortgages and US Housing

Morgan Stanley

Securitized Credit Research Associate, New York

July 2013 - July 2014

- Built team's tools to perform analysis on large scale databases (>130 million observations of nested historical data and hundreds of features) using functional programming language q
- Developed strong relationships with modeling and quantitative analysis teams, working as a liaison between the more technical- and more business-oriented members on all three teams.
- Performed exploratory statistical analysis on new mortgage and housing market features to demonstrate their potential use in models via small-scale prototypes
- Leveraged programming skills to learn new languages (q/R) to improve the team's efficiency and

reproducibility of results

- Active poster on the internal Morgan Stanley q programming mailing list, frequently responding to questions posted by junior and senior modeling/technology/quantitative analysis colleagues, addressing functional programming features, optimizing expressions and clarifying language constructs

Non-Agency Mortgages and US Housing
Securitized Credit Research Analyst, New York

Morgan Stanley
July 2011 – July 2013

Internships.....

Data Science Cloudera

Intern, San Francisco

June 2015 - August 2015

- Contributed Scala implementations of various statistical tests to Spark's MLlib Namely: a 1-sample Kolmogorov Smirnov (KS) test (merged), 2-sample KS test (final stages of review), 1-sample Anderson-Darling test (final stages of review)
- Contributed to Cloudera's open source project spark-timeseries using Scala. Added functionality such as EWMA smoothing, ARIMA models, up/downsampling, PACF/ACF plotting, serial correlation testing, heteroskedasticity testing
- Wrote blog entries communicating technical aspects of implementations and providing underlying intuition

Fixed Income Generalist Sales and Fixed Income Credit Strategy
Richard B. Fisher Scholar, New York

Morgan Stanley Summer 2010

Investment Banking and Alternative Investments

Douglas Paul Scholar, New York

Morgan Stanley
Summer 2009

Notable Projects

- A2Q: an optimizing compiler from Aquery to q For my independent study and Masters thesis I am working on developing a compiler for the order-aware query language Aquery. The compiler is implemented in C and generates q code, performing various optimizations in expressions by finding opportunities in the abstract syntax tree produced. See the github repo for more info and code.
- **POS Tagging in German** As my final project in an NLP class, I implemented and compared various approaches to tagging the TIGER corpus in German with Parts-of-Speech. Models compared ranged from the simpler bi-gram Markov Model to Maximum Entropy Markov Models. Project was implemented using a combination of Python and Java. See the github repo for more info and code.

Technical skills

- Programming Languages: Proficient in: C, q, R. Productive in Scala.
- Natural Languages: Native fluency in English and Spanish. Working proficiency in German (verbal and written skills).

Interests and extra-curricular activity

- I'm very interested in exploring realms that I know little about, which ends up making book series like A
 Very Short Introduction some of my favorite reads. In general, I love learning and have taken advantage
 of free online courses to explore topics such as machine learning, NLP, data analysis and Scala.
- o I also enjoy keeping a blog that lets me write explanations for things I have learned or show simple solutions to interesting problems. You can take a look at symfun.wordpress.com. The blog is "language-agnostic" (i.e. I pick whatever language is interesting or I feel like practicing), but you will find snippets of: C, q, Standard ML, Scala, and Java.